<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian caueat for al estates. Or A sermon, preached by that religious seruant of God, Master George Hockin, Bachelor of Diuinitie, Fellow of Excester Colledge, and preacher to the towne of Totnes in Deuon</title>
            <author>Hockin, George, b. 1569 or 70.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03419</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13542</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851814</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17106</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03419)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17106)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1311:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian caueat for al estates. Or A sermon, preached by that religious seruant of God, Master George Hockin, Bachelor of Diuinitie, Fellow of Excester Colledge, and preacher to the towne of Totnes in Deuon</title>
                  <author>Hockin, George, b. 1569 or 70.</author>
                  <author>I. C., fl. 1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The editor's dedication is signed: I.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17106:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17106:1"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIAN CAVEAT FOR AL ESTATES.</p>
            <p>OR A Sermon, preached by that Religious ſeruant of GOD, Maſter GEORGE HOCKIN, <hi>Bachelor of Diuinitie, Fellow of Exceſter</hi> Colledge, and Preacher to the Towne of <hi>Totnes</hi> in <hi>Deuon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 105.5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Remember yee his maruellous workes that he hath done: his wonders and the iudgements of his mouth.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>William Stansby.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17106:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17106:2"/>
            <head>TO The vertuous and truely religious, <hi>Miſtris</hi> P. I. <hi>encreaſe of all ſpirituall grace</hi> and true comfort here, with aſſurance of eternall glorie and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hereafter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe holy and heauenly Meditations, were by the Author of them at first, conceiued vpon the occaſion of the deceaſe of a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Gentleman, with whom hee was much conuerſant: Good Wine needeth no Garland, it will praiſe it ſelfe: ſo I perſwade my ſelfe, will this enſuing Sermon, which a learned, holy, and faithfull Seruant of God, formerly, <hi>Viua voce,</hi> in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique ſounded in your eares, and in the eares of many others, which it furniſht with the best and rareſt things which <hi>Canaan, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> doth yeeld. There is ſcarce in the Booke of God, a Mine, that is more rich and abundant in exhorting men to remember their Creator, then the Text handled in this Sermon. This Treatiſe will affoord good helpe to thoſe that will deigne, diligently to peruſe the ſame. For, herein the learned ſhall meete with ſome things not common, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps not to encreaſe, yet to renew his ſecret knowledge, and whet his iudgement; and alſo the godly Chriſtian ſhall not want wherewith to feed his deuouteſt Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:17106:3"/> and enkindle his best affections toward God. But lest I doe ſeeme like ſome deceitfull Broker,<note place="margin">Laudat venales qui vult extrudere merces, <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> to ſet worth on worthleſſe Wares, by goodly words; I will leaue the proofe hereof to the judicious, and not fastidious Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. I lighting vpon this Sermon, of that both learned and godly Diuine, Master <hi>George Hockin</hi> (of whoſe gracious abilitie in preaching Gods Word, and of whoſe conſcionable care in performing his Ministeriall office, many can witneſſe) as a poore Orphan Babe of a decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Friend, for the memorie of its Author, haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentured to ſhew my ſelfe ſo farre on this Theater, as to ſet it forth to publique view, and to make it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for the benefit of others. I preſume, good men will both accept my good meaning, and conne me thanks, who haue ſet vp for them ſuch a faire and cleere light, to light them on-ward in the way that will leade them to eternall bliſſe. The Lord grant, that it may haue that ſucceſſe in ſuch as are religiouſly affected, which, he that gaue first life vnto it in ſtudying, and brought it forth by preaching, intended, and I in conſenting and cauſing to haue it Printed, deſire: ſo ſhall young and old, the feeble, weake, and doubting Chriſtian, be taken by the hand, and we all ſhall be of the number of them which follow Faith, to the conſeruation of our ſoules: which the Lord for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake grant. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in his beſt deſires, I. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17106:3"/>
            <head>A CHRISTIAN CAVEAT FOR ALL ESTATES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ECCLESIASTES 12.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, before the euill dayes come, and the yeeres approch, of which thou wilt ſay, I haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>OLOMON was Sonne vnto the worthieſt King, that euer ſwayed Scepter vpon Earth; he was the Sonne of a King, a King himſelfe, and the Father of a King, and Predeceſſor in the royall Line vnto the Sonne of GOD, and for Nobilitie matchleſſe. He was King of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which was the Citie of GOD, the Lady of the World, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie, the perfection of Beautie, and the ioy of the whole Earth. In ſpeculatiue knowledge, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled the wiſedome of all the Children of the <hi>East,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17106:4"/> and all the wiſedome of <hi>Egypt.</hi> He was able to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe from the <hi>Cedar</hi> tree, that is in <hi>Lebanon,</hi> euen vnto the <hi>Hyſſope,</hi> that ſpringeth out of the wall. He was the moſt fit and abſolute man that euer liued, both for abilitie and vnderſtanding, abundance of riches, and ſufficiency of all Creatures. This King exhorteth young men to remember GOD in their youth. The flower of youth will vaniſh away, therefore, <hi>Remember thy Creator in youth;</hi> it is the beſt way, and the onely way, to turne away anger and euill, alwaies to remember the power, goodnes, and iuſtice of GOD the Creator. The dependance theſe words haue on the former, is in this ſort; <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> hauing exhorted Youth in their youth and prime-time, to remember their Maker. He ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take away griefe out of thy heart, that is, all thoſe things which prouoke the anger of GOD; cauſe euill to depart from thy fleſh, that is, all pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which comes from GODS anger; <hi>And remember thy Creator.</hi> This Text contayneth two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, An exhortation to godlineſſe in youth, <hi>And remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, A reaſon taken from the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold infirmities of old age, <hi>Whiles the euill dayes come not, nor the yeeres approch, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſumme and ſenſe is this; <hi>Solomon,</hi> a man experienced, willed young men to remember GOD that made them, and that in their youth; not that they ſhould forget him in their old age, but they
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17106:4"/> ſhould begin betime to know GOD, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, whiles they continue on earth; there is good cauſe ſo to doe, for he made them, brought them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world, and bought them too; and they ſhould remember him here, that hee might remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them hereafter, before old age, weake age, and dote-age come; before weaknes, ſicknes, ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, and other infirmities happen, which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie old age.</p>
            <p>Or <hi>Solomon</hi> puts the diſſolute young man in minde of iudgement; there hee ſhewes him, how to eſcape it, by auoiding the anger of GOD, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to remember <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you haue ſeene <hi>Solomons</hi> meaning: now, to ſpeake of ſome ſuch profitable inſtructions, as theſe words ſhall afford.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And remember.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>] The true and ſerious remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of GOD, is an eſpeciall remedie againſt ſinne; and the forgetting of GOD, a cauſe of ſinne. GOD himſelfe commandeth it in the Scripture, ſaying, <hi>Remember Iehouah thy God, for it is he which giueth the power to get ſubſtance, Deut.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Dauid,</hi> from GOD, willed the people not to forget GODS Works, but to keepe his Commandements, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78.7. Here wee may ſee plainly, that the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of GOD keepeth vs from ſinning, as the wicked doe. GOD commandeth <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him continually, that hee might liue well, and proſper, ſaying, <hi>The booke of the Law ſhall not depart out of thy mouth, but thou ſhalt meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in day and night, that ſo thou maiest obſerue to doe all things therein, and then thou ſhalt make thy wayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17106:5"/> and haue good ſucceſſe, Ioſh.</hi> 1.8. Remember that thoſe are commonly the beſt opportunities of mercy and pardon, which are moſt early offered; and theſe are hardly recouered, when through wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full contempt, or ſlight negligence, carnall and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh eaſe, they haue beene long contemned. Let all remember their Creator in their youth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That the onely meanes to eſcape Gods wrath, is to remember him. God gaue <hi>Iſrael</hi> a Law, to bee continued to their poſteritie; namely, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God and keepe his Commandements, that ſo they might not bee a faithleſſe and ſtubborne Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, who ſet not aright their hearts, and whoſe ſpirit cleaueth not ſtedfaſtly vnto God, like their fore-fathers; and the children of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> who kept not Gods Couenant, forgetting God and his wondrous works, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5. to 12. Here wee may ſee plainly, that the remembrance of God is a meanes to eſcape his wrath. When the Lord had giuen the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> abundance and plentie of all things, leſt they ſhould fall into pride, vnthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other ſinnes, he giueth them this caueat, ſaying; <hi>When thou haſt eaten, and art full, and haſt built goodly houſes, and dwell therein; and when thy Heards and thy Flocke, and all thou is multiplied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, and take thou heed, thou forgetteſt not the Lord thy God; and leſt thy heart be lifted vp, and thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Lord thy God; but remember the Lord thy God, Deut.</hi> 8.10 to 18. The Apoſtle <hi>Iude,</hi> writing againſt the wicked Seducers, that liued in his time, preſcribeth this as a remedie to eſcape Gods wrath, <hi>Remember the words of the Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17106:5"/> Iude</hi> 17. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhewing, what a combat hee had with Diffidence and Diſtruſt, acknowledgeth this to be his remedie, whereby he got the victorie, the remembrance of God; and ſo after confeſſion of the combat, he ſaith. <hi>And, I ſaid, this is mine infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, but I will remember the yeeres of the right hand of the moſt High, I will remember the works of the Lord; ſurely, I will remember thy wonders of old, I will meditate alſo of all thy works, Pſal.</hi> 77.10. <hi>We muſt remember to ſerue and walke with God by dayes, not by weekes and moneths onely, Pſal.</hi> 90.12.</p>
            <p>As the chiefeſt meanes to eſcape Gods wrath, is to remember the Lord; ſo, the ſpeedieſt meanes to draw downe his iudgements, is to forget the Lord. Now, conſider this, <hi>yee that forget God,</hi> that is, him and his iudgements againſt ſinne, <hi>leſt I teare you,</hi> there is the greatneſſe of their iudgement, <hi>and there be no Reſcuer,</hi> that is, no hope of deliuerance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.22. <hi>The wicked ſhall turne into hell,</hi> and all the Heathens that forget God, <hi>Pſael.</hi> 9.18. When the people forgate the Lord their God, he ſold them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hand of <hi>Siſera,</hi> Captaine of the Hoſt of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zor;</hi> and into the hand of the <hi>Philistims,</hi> and into the hand of the King of <hi>Moab,</hi> and they fought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.9. Seeing <hi>thou hast forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the Law of thy God, I will alſo forget thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, Hoſ.</hi> 4.6. If men forget God, hee will forget them, forget to ſhew mercy, but he will remember to execute iuſtice and wrath. <hi>Thou haſt forgotten the mightie God that begate, and hast forgotten God that formed thee;</hi> what then, <hi>the Lord ſaw it and was angrie, Deut.</hi> 32.18, 19. If Gods words can
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17106:6"/> worke vs to his will, he will ſpare his blowes. Hee hath as little delight in ſmiting as wee in ſuffering. Hee reioyceth in his owne goodneſſe, grieueth at our wretchedneſſe. God amplifieth this ſinne of forgetfulneſſe; <hi>Can a Maid forget her ornaments, or a Bride her attire, yet my people haue forgotten mee dayes without number, Iere.</hi> 2.32. as if he had ſaid, their Ornaments, Iewels, and Rings, are but toyes and trifles. Is there any Ornament like me? Is there any Iewell amongſt them all, that can be compared with me? Men remember their friends often, and call them to minde. An old man will remember his bagge, yet hee will forget God: ſhall ſuch things take vp mens memories? and ſhall God bee thruſt out?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Wee muſt remember God our Creator; hee made vs happy, but mutable; but Satan by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit did caſt vs from that happy condition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, beſides the loſſe of that felicitie, we were plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into extreme miſerie, which conſiſteth in two things: Firſt, in ſinne: Secondly, the curſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon it. Through ſinne, the Vnderſtanding is filled with blindneſſe, the conſcience wounded, ſeared, and defiled: the Memorie forgetting good things, or not remembring any thing aright: the Will captiue, of no ſtrength to good, but onely to euill: the Affections, altogether diſordered: the Cogitations about heauenly matters, are errors, falſehood, and lies: the Wiſhes and Deſires of the Heart are earthly and fleſhly. The Curſe maketh vs ſubiect to Deathes and Famines; in Body to ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other paines. Wee ſhould remember
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17106:6"/> God, becauſe he promiſed the <hi>Meſsiah, Gen.</hi> 3.15. becauſe <hi>he hath bought vs with a price,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. becauſe hee hath preſerued vs, and in the end will glorifie vs. If a man be ſanctified with the diuine Nature, in which glorie is begun, he is iuſtified; if iuſtified, then called according to purpoſe; if called, then predeſtinate; if predeſtinate to meanes, then foreknowne, as one choſen to the end, euen to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Of God we receiue euery good thing, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.17. therefore we ſhould remember him. Euery ache and paine is a <hi>memento,</hi> to put vs in minde of God. How great is our ſinne, if we forget him.</p>
            <p>Wee ſhould remember God, becauſe of his all-ſeeing <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Wiſedome, for hee ſeeth all things wee doe, though neuer ſo ſecretly; hee heareth euery word we ſpeake, though neuer ſo tacitely. He <hi>that plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the eare, ſhall he not heare; or he that formed the eye, ſhall hee not ſee, Pſal.</hi> 94.9. <hi>Hee knoweth vaine man, and ſeeth iniquitie, Iob</hi> 11.11. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my ſitting and my riſing, thou vnderſtandeſt my thoughts afarre off. Thou compaſſeſt my pathes, and my lying downe, and art accuſtomed to all my waies. For, <hi>There is not a word in my tongue, but, loe, thou knoweſt it wholly, O Lord, Pſal.</hi> 139.2, 3, 4. We ſhould remember his Iuſtice, he is righteous, and muſt needs puniſh, he is a mightie God, and is able to puniſh. There is nothing wanting in him, which is fit to bee in one, on whom wee are to place our truſt. He is able to helpe vs becauſe he hath power; what a power is that which keepes vs to ſaluation, who haue ſo little ſtrength, and leſſe wiſedome, whereby we might ſtand; nay, he is Omnipotent,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17106:7"/> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.1. He is willing, becauſe he loues vs ſo dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.16. Nay, to the death, <hi>Precious in the ſight of the Lord, is the death of his Saints, Pſal.</hi> 116.15. He is skilfull, becauſe <hi>all the treaſures of knowledge and wiſedome are hid in him, Coloſſ.</hi> 2.3. He is mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, becauſe <hi>his eyes are alwaies open vpon vs, he doth neither ſlumber nor ſleepe, Pſal.</hi> 121.4. He is carefull, becauſe <hi>he is Lord and King ouer all, he is the King of Kings,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.15. And he biddeth vs, caſt all our care vpon him, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7. Wee cannot ſearch theſe things to the full, for to ſee things vnuiſible, and ſearch things vnſearchable, are alike vnpoſſible.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> We ſhould remember God, for he hath giuen vs many helpes of memory: Firſt, hee hath giuen vs the Scriptures, his Word, an Epiſtle ſent vs from Heauen, that by reading and hearing it, wee might remember him. For hee that forgetteth the Word of God, will ſoone forget God, and he that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth the Word, will remember God the author of the Word. Secondly, wee haue the Sacraments, which are tokens of Gods loue, which ſhould cauſe vs to remember God. Thirdly, the creatures ſhould put vs in minde of God, euery one repreſenting, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the power, goodneſſe, or mercy of God; euery tree, and euery leafe, euery flower, and euery graſſe, euery ſtone; nay, euery ſand doth ſet forth his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The greater is our ſinne if we forget him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſo many meanes to remember him. Should a Sonne forget is Father, who hath left him many to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens to remember him by? If a Husband departing from home, ſhould leaue many Memorials with his Wife, on euery Doore, Wall, and Poſte, a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17106:7"/> that ſhee can goe no where, but ſhee muſt needes remember him; yea, if ſhee haue his Signet on her finger, that ſo, as often as ſhee lookes on her finger, ſhe may remember him; how great were her fault, to forget him, or how were it poſſible, not to remember him. The Almighty God hath thus dealt with vs, in the world, which is his Houſe, hee hath left euery where remembrances. If a Woman remember her Husband, ſeeing his Ring, ſhe ſhould remember God, ſeeing her finger, which his Finger made; and her hands, the worke of his Hands. <hi>When I beheld the Heauens, euen the workes of thy Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, the Moone and the Starres which thou haſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, Pſal.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p>Great benefits ſhould cauſe vs remember God: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>4</label> What maketh vs ſo to ſinne, but the forgetting of God, therefore it is often ſaid of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> they forgate God, and ſerued <hi>Baalim;</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, they neuer would haue committed Idolatry, if they had not forgotten God; <hi>They haue peruerted their way, and forgotten the Lord their God, Ier.</hi> 3.21. The latter is the cauſe of the former, and ſo, forgetters of God, are put for wicked men. Now, as forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God cauſeth ſinne, witneſſe Adulterers, Drunkards, and ſuch like, which will confeſſe they forgate God: ſo the remembrance of God is the cauſe of obedience, for hee that remembreth God, will feare to offend him, and endeauour to pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>The vſe of this point is for our inſtruction, that <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> wee ſhould bee the more carefull to remember the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17106:8"/> Lord. Firſt, God commandeth it, and Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements muſt be obeyed; <hi>If he conſent and obey, he ſhall eate the good things of the Land, Eſay</hi> 1.19. <hi>Whatſoeuer we aske; we receiue of him, becauſe we keep his Commandements, and doe thoſe things which are pleaſing in his ſight,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.22. If wee reade the Scriptures, heare the Word, bleſſed ſhall wee bee if we keepe it, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that readeth, and they that heare the words of the Prophecie, and keepe thoſe things which are written therein; Reuel.</hi> 1.3. Our Goods, Cattell, Corne, and all things belonging to vs, ſhall be bleſſed of God; if we obey his voyce, and doe as hee would haue vs; yea, our children ſhall bee bleſſed after vs, <hi>Bleſſed is the vpright man, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall his ſeede be after him, Pro.</hi> 20.7. Yea, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that meditates in the Law of God day and night; For he ſhall be like a Tree, planted by the Riuers of Waters, Pſal.</hi> 1, 2, 3. <hi>No good thing will the Lord withhold from them that liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly, Pſal.</hi> 84.11. On the contrary, euen thoſe things which in their owne nature are the good bleſſings of God, ſhall be accurſed of God: And the Lord will in his wrath, and in his hot anger, curſe our bleſſings. This Commandement is for you, <hi>If yee will heare, and if yee will not lay it to heart, to giue glory to my Name, ſaith the Lord of Hostes. I will euen ſend a curſe vpon you, and I will curſe your bleſsings; yea, I haue curſed them already, becauſe yee doe not conſider it in heart, Malach.</hi> 2.2. Secondly, the promiſes which God hath made to ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, ſhould be a meanes to ſtirre vs vp to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17106:8"/> remember him, he hath promiſed to bee with <hi>his to the end of the world, Matth.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Neuer to faile them, nor forſake them, Heb.</hi> 13.5. Hee promiſed to giue his Sonne, <hi>the firſt begotten, and the onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.7. And in him what rare mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter can we wiſh for, which is not in him to be found. Would wee haue Wiſedome, hee is the eſſentiall Wiſedome of the Father, the obiect of all true Wiſedome, which tendeth to ſaluation, in him is our Wiſedome, not onely while wee walke by faith at home in this body, but alſo when wee ſhall walke by ſight with the Lord, ſeeing him as he is. All <hi>the treaſure of Wiſedome and Vnderſtanding are hid in him, Col.</hi> 2.3. Would we haue Righteouſneſſe, he is eſſentially righteous, as God in our name; habitually and actually Righteous. He <hi>is Iehouah our Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Ier.</hi> 23.6. The Sunne of Righteouſneſſe, that perſon which hath brought with him euerlaſting Righteouſneſſe. Would wee haue Redemption, with him <hi>is great redemption, Pſal.</hi> 130.7. Through him haue we redemption, that is, <hi>Forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, Col.</hi> 1.14. By him wee doe waite for <hi>the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of our bodies, Rom.</hi> 8.23. Chriſt was power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the eternall prouidence of God, before crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our election; powerfull in time appointed for our Vocation, Iuſtification, Sanctification; powerfull for our perſeuerance, and finall conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. He is God, what ſeeke wee? Hee is God, what deſire wee? This Sonne was promiſed, and this Sonne is come. God firſt promiſed protection from hurt in his ſeruice; hee vndertakes to keepe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17106:9"/> damage from his, while they are occupied in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. When all the Males ſhould goe vp to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> thrice in the yeere, and none but weake women and children left at home, yet God doth vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, that no enemie ſhould haue the heart to breake in on them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.24. Secondly, God promiſeth to beſtow on vs euery thing that is good, nay, all good. Thirdly, God promiſeth to his a cheerfull vſe, of all the good benefits vouchſafed them. Did not <hi>Ioſiah</hi> eate and drinke, and proſper, while hee executed iudgement and iuſtice? <hi>Iere.</hi> 22.15. Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath not onely the promiſes of this life, but of the life to come, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. He that giues the head, giues haire alſo. God giueth vs his Kingdome and Righteouſneſſe, which are principall; how ſhould he not adde theſe inferiour things alſo, which are but acceſſarie to the other. God will not ſtand for ſmall matters with them to whom he will giue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. This God, who is ſo gracious; this God, who is ſo glorious; this God, who is ſo mercifull and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berall, muſt be remembred. Thirdly, the dangers which follow the forgetfulneſſe of God, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite vs to remember God. Such as forget God, ſhall be puniſhed. Forgetfulneſſe, is a cauſe of, firſt, Spirituall puniſhment: ſecondly, of Corporall: thirdly, of Eternall. It is a cauſe of ſpirituall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment in the ſoule, of corporall puniſhments in the body; and of eternall, both in body and ſoule, at the day of Iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Secondly, it is a reproofe of thoſe who forget God, and caſt the remembrance of him behind their
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17106:9"/> backs; for what elſe doe they, who ſweare at euery word, and the more they ſweare, the better men they account themſelues. If they did remember God, who ſaith, <hi>Sweare not at all, Matth.</hi> 5.34. And the words of the Apoſtle <hi>Iames, Before all things, my Brethren, ſweare not, Iam.</hi> 5.12. If they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member Gods Truth, Iuſtice, and Power; his Truth, that he is a Defender of; his Iuſtice, that he is a Reuenger of the breakers of it; his Power, that he is able to execute his Vengeance, if they ſweare falſely, they would neuer ſweare vainely. Firſt, the matter of an Oath muſt be Truth. Secondly, the manner muſt be in Iudgement. Thirdly, the ſquare in Righteouſneſſe; all theſe the Prophet rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord liueth in Truth, in Iudgement, and in Righteouſneſſe, Iere.</hi> 4.2. If Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath breakers did remember God, they would not commit ſacrilege, in ſtealing from him three parts of his Sabbath, to their owne vſes; and for the fourth, as good neuer a whit, as neuer the better. If they did remember the Commander, God, the matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, which is the ſanctifying of the Sabbath, and ſpending of it in holy exerciſes, they would not ſpend it ſo prophanely as they doe, ſeeing it is a ſigne that God is their God, that doth ſanctifie them a ſolemne holiday, wherein hee declareth his loue and care ouer them; a Day, wherein hee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto them his holy things, as his Word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and all heauenly and holy riches, a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall meanes of their ſanctification and ſaluation; a Day, which hee hath appointed, wherein euery
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17106:10"/> one ſhould profeſſe their Faith, Loue, and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to his heauenly Maieſtie. If they did remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber God, which commit adulterie, they would be aſhamed of ſuch behauiour, they would not doe it for a world, for it is moſt hurtfull, moſt vnfruitfull, moſt ſhamefull, moſt abominable, and moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. It hurteth, Firſt, the body: Secondly, the ſoule: Thirdly, the eſtate: Fourthly, the good name: Fiftly, the life. It ariſeth, firſt, from an vnregenerate heart, which is the harbour of filthy luſts, for <hi>out of the heart proceed adulteries, fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Matth.</hi> 15.19. Secondly, from originall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence, which is like a home-borne Traitor, lurking ſecretly, vnder-mining couertly, creeping priuily, entiſing vehemently, betraying treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly into the hands of the Deuill; a woman would not commit adulterie if ſhee remembred; firſt, the Commandement, <hi>Thou ſhalt not commit adulterie, Exod.</hi> 20.14. Secondly, her husband to whom ſhee is married, <hi>who is one fleſh with her, Gen.</hi> 2.24. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Couenant which ſhe hath made, <hi>forſaking all others, and cleauing vnto her husband, Matth.</hi> 19.5. Fourthly, the puniſhment, which is damnation, without true repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>Thy Creator.</hi>] As if he ſhould ſay, he made thee, therefore thou muſt remember him, or elſe thy ſinne will be the greater in forgetting him. <hi>The Oxe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his Owner, and the Aſſe his Maſters maunger, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi> 1.3. and will not Man know his Creator. And God ſaid, <hi>Let vs make Man, Gen.</hi> 1.26. hee did not ſay, Let Man be made; as he ſaid, <hi>Let there be Light:</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17106:10"/> neither did hee command the Elements to bring forth Man; as hee commanded the Earth to bud forth Herbs, Graſſe, and ſuch like; or the Waters to bring forth Fiſh; but, as it were, conſulting, he ſaith, <hi>Let vs make Man.</hi> The Creation of Man was the worke of the whole <hi>Trinitie,</hi> ſo was the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Man. We are baptiſed in the Name of the <hi>Father,</hi> becauſe he adopteth vs to be Sonnes; in the Name of the <hi>Sonne,</hi> becauſe he hath bought vs with his Bloud; in the Name of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> becauſe by him wee are Sanctified. Our Creator muſt bee remembred aboue all, becauſe hee is aboue all, and before all. God is ſo the Creator, that hee is the alone Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That Mans creation bindeth him to remember God; <hi>Remember thy Creator:</hi> hee did make thee an excellent Creature. <hi>Hath not one God created vs, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lac.</hi> 2.10. <hi>He alone faſhioned vs in the wombe, Iob</hi> 31.15. <hi>Vnto vs there is but one God, which is the Father, of whom are all things,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. <hi>He that hath built all things is God, Heb.</hi> 3.4. <hi>There is none beſides me, I am the Lord, and there is none other. I forme the Light, and create Darkneſſe; I, the Lord, doe all theſe things, Eſa.</hi> 45.6, 7. <hi>I am the Lord that made all things, and ſpread out the Heauens aboue, Eſa.</hi> 44.24. <hi>He a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone ſpreadeth out the Heauens, Iob</hi> 9.8. From all this we may gather, that the creation of man, and of all things elſe, muſt bee attributed to God onely. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture bindeth Children to remember their Parents. Duetie bindeth Schollers to remember their Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors; Charitie bindeth Chriſtians to remember the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17106:11"/> poore, the Law bindeth men to eſchew euill and ſinne; Sinne, as it hardens, ſo it weakens; the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell bindeth men to beleeue; and the Creation bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth men to remember the Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, Mans creation bindeth him to remember God, becauſe Man hath his being from God. It is proper to God to produce a Thing from no Being to a Being, for he calleth Things that are not, as if they were by his Almightineſſe. God is of infinite power, able to doe whatſoeuer he will, and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whatſoeuer hee will not haue done; by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue power, and by his abſolute power, able to doe more then he will. Some Creatures haue a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely, as Heauen and Earth, Meteors in the one, and Metals in the other. Some a Being and Life al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as Plants and Beaſts, which with Life haue Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ioyned. Some Being, Life, Senſe, light of Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Reaſon, as Angels and Men. Man, hauing his breath from God; for, <hi>God breathed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the breath of Life, Gen.</hi> 2.7. that is, a liuing Soule, by the vertue of the eternall Spirit, was inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into an Elementarie body, to vſe it as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſhould make Man remember his Creator. Man hauing from God his being, and his breath, his life, and liuing; his motion, and mouing, ſhould remember his Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Man ſhould remember God his Creator, becauſe he made him an excellent Creature, compleat and full of the true knowledge of God and of holines, without any the leaſt want or defect. As in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> mankind was made; ſo in the latter, it was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17106:11"/> reſtored: the Elect came from Chriſt by Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as all men from <hi>Adam</hi> by Generation. Though <hi>Adam</hi> did fall grieuouſly, yet Beleeuers are more happy in the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> riſing, then in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> falling; in Chriſt ſauing, then in <hi>Adam</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. God made <hi>Adam</hi> plaine, but <hi>they ſought out many conceits, Eccleſ.</hi> 7.31. And ſo doe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in all folly. In that God made Man, and Chriſt regenerateth Man, and reſtoreth that which was decayed in him; this ſhould moue Man to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Creator.</p>
            <p>The firſt vſe, may reproue ſuch men as know not <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> their Maker. Many weare Gods cloth, that know not their Maſter, that neuer did good worke in his ſeruice; hee hath many Retayners, that weare his Liuerie for a countenance, neuer waite on him. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that eate his meate, that neuer acknowledge the Giuer. Many protected by him, ſee it not. Many afflicted, yet ſeeke him not diligently, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Hee ſtrikes them, but they ſorrow not; hee conſumes them, but they refuſe his correction, Iere.</hi> 5.3. He giues to ſuch as are vnthankfull, clotheth ſuch as are proud, helpeth ſuch as are vnworthy, and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for ſuch as are wicked. He that giueth all good things, hath little or nought giuen him againe. Where hee ſhould bee loued, hee is hated; and of whom hee ſhould bee honoured, he is diſhonoured. Gods loue towards vs, hath beene from all eternitie. Some, as wine, doth receiue the greater praiſe by the age of it: old wine is the beſt, and ancient loue is the moſt approued. How much doe wee eſteeme
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17106:12"/> of ſuch a friend, as hath borne vs good wil for ſome twentie or fortie yeeres together? The more recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wee ſhould make of Gods loue, which hath beene eternall. Before Chriſt wee were enemies to God, there was nothing to be ſeene in vs, but ſinne and miſerie, nor any thing to draw Gods affection toward vs, but his owne free and good pleaſure: now, that loue wee haue deſerued, wee the leſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme; but ſuch loue as is freely conferred on vs, we doe make more ſtore of.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> The ſecond Vſe, not onely the Creation bindeth Man to remember God, but all other his benefits wherewith Man is compaſſed about. Many are the works of mercy, which God hath beſtowed on Man; beſides the Creation, all of them binding Man to remember God. Firſt, Mans Redemption by Chriſt. Of all the works of mercy, this chiefly ought to be remembred, for it is the chiefeſt worke; the freedome of Sinners, both from the guilt and power of ſinne. By whom wee haue Redemption through his Bloud, euen the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.7. To haue ſinne forgiuen, is to bee redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, or ſet free from all euill. That which <hi>Paul</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in the former words, Redemption, is afterward called Remiſſion of ſinne. What is forgiueneſſe of ſinne, but an act of Grace, acquitting vs from all the guilt, and the whole puniſhment of all our ſinne; and as men ſpeake of Redemption, ſo they may ſpeake of Remiſſion. Secondly, the worke of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, is another great benefit of God, which is a keeping men free and ſafe from dangers, and from
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17106:12"/> hurt by enemies: <hi>Preſerue me, O Lord, for I trust in thee, Pſal.</hi> 16.1. <hi>What ſhall I doe vnto thee, O thou Keeper of men, Iob</hi> 7.20. <hi>Hee preſerueth both Man and Beaſt, Pſal.</hi> 36.6. <hi>Thou preſeruedſt them all, Nehe.</hi> 9.6. Thirdly, the worke of Suſtentation bindeth Man to remember God, for God vp-hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his Children, that they take not a fall by ſinne and calamitie, or that they take no hurt by ſuch fals. <hi>The Lord ſuſtayned me, Pſal.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Hee maketh mee to rest in greene pastures, and leadeth me by the ſtill wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. Hee reſtoreth my ſoule, and leadeth mee in the pathes of Righteouſnes, for his Names ſake, Pſ.</hi> 23.2, 3. Many other benefits are men compaſſed withall, to binde them to remember God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the dayes of thy youth.</hi>] It is good for children to learne to know God, euen in youth,<note place="margin">Text.</note> whiles they are young, for ſo much <hi>Solomon</hi> teacheth here, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>In the dayes of thy youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That becauſe youth is moſt prone to forget God, it is needfull they ſhould be exhorted to remember God. Youth is moſt prone to forget God, for they are in the flower of their age, in the roofe of pride, and in the heate of luſt, hauing by nature corrupt hearts, and carnall deſires, liuing in pleaſures, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their time in mirth, all which makes them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God. Though young men doe not alwaies breake out into notorious wickedneſſe, yet they are ſubiect to youthfull wantonneſſe, and vnſtaiedneſſe of affection, which if it breake not out, yet it makes them forgetfull of God, and leſſe carefull of good things. This looſeneſſe is the way to lewdneſſe, this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17106:13"/> weakneſſe is the high way to wickednes, this Gods children (being regenerate) ſee, which before they ſaw not. Hence is it, that <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth, <hi>Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not the ſinnes of my youth, Pſal.</hi> 25.7. Of all mans life, Youth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly is moſt vaine; <hi>The imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of mans heart is euill from his youth, Ier.</hi> 8.21. <hi>We are all tranſgreſſors from the wombe, Eſa.</hi> 48.8. <hi>In ſinne hath my Mother conceiued me, Pſal.</hi> 51.5. <hi>Euen from the Belly haue they erred, Pſ.</hi> 58.3. For the ſinnes of youth, God often puniſheth men in their age, ſo making them to inherit the iniquities of their youth <hi>Iob</hi> 13.26. The Prophet ſaith, <hi>We and our Father (haue ſinned) from our youth, Ier.</hi> 3.25. Shal we thinke they in their youth committed groſſe ſins, as Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, Drunkenneſſe, Murther, and ſuch like, which were ſo holy men, as <hi>Iob</hi> and <hi>Ieremie:</hi> ſurely no, but they confeſſed the ſinnes of their youth, their wantonneſſe and forgetfulneſſe of God, their too much loue of pleaſure, their youthfulneſſe. <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Fooliſhneſſe is bound in the heart of a child, Pro.</hi> 22.15. therefore child-hood and youth are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, not in themſelues, but becauſe they are often ſpent in vanitie. Suruey thoſe which are more then ordinarie young men, which haue the beſt wits, and are thought to bee of the beſt diſpoſition, and their youth will hardly be found without vanitie; nay, not onely thoſe young men, that are beſt in ciuill gifts, but in ſpirituall graces, as <hi>Timothy,</hi> find <hi>child-hood and youth to be vanitie, Eccl.</hi> 11.10. <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> did tame his body, and bring it into ſubiection, ſo that <hi>Paul</hi> was faine to bid him to drinke wine,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17106:13"/> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.23. yet he had this <hi>memento</hi> giuen him, <hi>flie the luſts of youth,</hi> 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.22. Young men ſee not vanitie when they are yong, but they may perceiue it when they are old: for now, their conſciences are like water in a baſon, if the water be troubled, the face cannot be ſeene, but when it is ſetled, it may: ſo, all is troubled in youth, but when maturitie of yeeres come, then it will ſtand ſtill, and they may ſee their faces. <hi>Dauid</hi> being old praied againſt ſinnes of youth. Becauſe it is ſo hard, for a young man to remember God, and to be holy; <hi>Dauid</hi> breaketh off his meditation abruptly, into this, <hi>wherewithall ſhall a young man cleanſe his waies, Pſal.</hi> 119.9. And <hi>Dauid</hi> vſing the word <hi>cleanſing,</hi> compareth the young man to a glaſſe, which though it be very cleane, yet will gather filth in the Sunne beames. As a ricke of Hay put vp wet, ſet it ſelfe on fire: ſo haue the hearts of young men enough in them to inflame them.</p>
            <p>Young men ſhould remember their Creator in <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> their youth, leſt accuſtoming to forget God in youth, they doe not remember him in old age. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes is another nature, and can hardly be altered. Can the <hi>Black-More</hi> change his skinne, or the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard his ſpots? then may yee alſo doe good, that are accuſtomed to doe euill, <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23. This young men get by continuing in ſinne, they cannot leaue it, many cannot leaue ſwearing, lying, ſtealing, when they are old, becauſe they practiſed them when they were young. If I ſhould be demanded, why there are ſo few good old men: I anſwer, becauſe there were ſo many naughtie young men, for youth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17106:14"/> ſpent in vanitie, commonly ends old age in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe. The Prophet calleth ſome ſinnes <hi>Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſinnes, ſinnes of a double die, Eſay</hi> 1.18. If it be right Purple, it is dyed both in the Wooll and in the Thread, and then it is deepe. So, if Satan die vs in our Wooll, in our youth, before we be men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we be made cloth, it is likely to ſticke by vs. It is in a man, as in other things, in breaking of Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, luring of Hawkes, trayning of Dogges, which muſt be done while they are young: ſo muſt man in his youth, be trained vp in the feare of the Lord. The Diſeaſes of the Spring, are more curable then thoſe of Autumne: So the ſinnes of youth are more curable then thoſe of age, but when a man is ſoaked in them, hee is paſt cure. If Satan can make our youth vnprofitable, there cannot any good be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for of the after ages, without the great mercy of Almightie God. Hence commeth thoſe ſpeeches of ſinnes, which a man hath continued in; I would faine, but I cannot leaue them, whereby it comes to paſſe, that where one doth recouer, fortie rot away. If the Deuill nip the Bloſſome, what hope is there of Fruit. When a man hath long had a truſtie Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, he is loth to forgoe him, he will rather increaſe his wages: So, the Deuill will be loth to forgoe him in his age, who ſerued him in his youth. The ſinnes of youth ſticke faſt by a man, hee can hardly leaue them, youth being like a new Morter, wherein if you ſtampe Garlicke, it will a long time ſmell of it; and though they repent and come home, yet they carry the ſmell of the Garlicke Morter whereſoeuer
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17106:14"/> they goe. The veſſell will relliſh of the firſt liquour: What iniurie doe men to themſelues, by liuing prophanely in youth, when they bee old, they dare not reprehend ſo ſharply as others, nor puniſh ſo ſeuerely as they ſhould, becauſe the ſinnes of their youth are ſo in their foreheads, that all men ſee them. God will haue the firſt fruites, and the firſt borne are due to him. The Autumne cannot ſee the fruit of thoſe trees, whoſe bloſſomes the Spring-time neuer ſaw. If men begin not to loue vertue in youth, it will bee a harſh thing for them for to wooe her in old age, when the threed of life ſhall be tentred, and drawne euen to the vtmoſt length.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Deuill hath a ſpeciall affection to this <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> age, knowing that if hee get youth, hee hath often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mans age too. Sathan doth not eaſily forſake his hold, nor ſurrender his poſſeſſion; though he be not an Angell of light, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. yet he would be like one. Though he ſeldome ſpeake truth, yet he is more beleeued then God the Authour of truth. Though he damned many Soules, yet hee is ſerued by youth, and followed by them in troupes. Hee hath ſuch varieties of pleaſures, which he preſenteth to them that they are bewitched by them, hee is an vnreaſonable, inſatiable, vſurping tyrant, yet youth will not hearken to Gods word, who ſaith, reſiſt the deuill, <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.7. It is lamentable, that no age doth ſo much deſpiſe the Word, as youth, which muſt ſtand in neede of it. It is now a rare thing to find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong yong men, a <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> or a <hi>Samuel,</hi> where they ſhould liue as <hi>Nazarites,</hi> conſecrated to the Lord,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17106:15"/> 
               <hi>Amos</hi> 2.11. they are rather like men, who haue vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and dedicated themſelues vnto Sathan. As the ſonnes of <hi>Eli</hi> deſpiſed the rebuke of their father: So yong men now (for the moſt part) are impatient of of the rebukes of the Word, contemning the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. The prodigall ſonne had foure prouocations; Firſt, his portion; Secondly, his fathers indulgence; Thirdly, ill companie; Fourthly, youth, theſe the Deuill vſeth as ſo many baites, to take young men withall, theſe hurt yong men much. Till the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſpent, the prodigall thought not vpon retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning home. The prodigall man, while he ſpendeth, is magnified, when hee is ſpent is pitied, and that is all his recompence for his lauiſhing. The indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the father to conniue &amp; winke at the faults of their Children, doth breede in their Children a forgetfulneſſe of their Creator. Ill companie hurt youth, for ſuch are they for the moſt part as they are, with whom familiarly they liue, and with whom for the moſt part they ſpend their time. All waters in temperature, in colour, and in taſte, agree with the nature and the diſpoſition of thoſe grounds, and of that earth, through which they make their ſecret paſſages, and their wayes: In like manner men pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thoſe things, which by frequent cuſtome, they haue deriued to themſelues, from thoſe with whom they haue conuerſed. Youth is ſo wanton and wild, ſo rude and vnruly, ſo loſe and lewde, that vnleſſe God ſaue, the Deuill will deſtroy; vnleſſe God draw them, the Deuill will keepe them.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Young men ſhould remember their Creator in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17106:15"/> youth, conſidering their naturall corruption, they are corrupt Children, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.4. They know nothing but how to corrupt themſelues, their wayes, their liues, their actions, their neighbours by euill coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and euill examples, themſelues by euill exerciſes. This naturall corruption is moſt deformed, a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter both vgly and fearefull. If naturall corruption will haue yong men eate till they ſurfeite, and drinke till they bee drunke, you ſhall finde multitudes of them that will doe it, though they conſume goods, body, eſtate, and damme the Soule. If naturall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption will haue yong men bee wantons, there will bee ſome that will fit and addreſſe themſelues for it, by lurking here and there in corners; frequenting diſhoneſt places, vſing idle and immodeſt Exerciſes; corrupt and rotten communication, ſtuffed with vaine vnfruitfull Ieſtes, and prophane paſſages. It is a thing moſt lamentable, and neuer enough to bee bewailed, to ſee many young perſons, whoſe dayly practiſe and trade of life, is to corrupt their fleſh in lying, deceiuing, ſeeking vnlawfull and vngodly gaines; ſlaundring and backbiting their neighbours; ſpending their time wantonly and wickedly, for which, one day they muſt giue account to GOD.</p>
            <p>The firſt vſe, ſerueth for our inſtruction, ſeeing <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> yong men are hardeſt to bee reformed, they ſhould learne to bee Godly in their youth. It is good for a man to beare the yoke in his youth, <hi>Lament.</hi> 3.17. It is good for a man to remember his Creator in his youth. Some will ſay, ſhall youth ſpend no time in pleaſure? What, not halfe a mans youth? Not a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17106:16"/> day now and then, not an houre? Surely, GOD will not allow a minute of time to bee ſpent in vaine. Yong men will ſay, wee will become good, and liue Grauely hereafter, and behaue our ſelues ſoberly, we will amend when we are old. This is to make a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with the Deuill, thou wilt be Gods, but not yet. As <hi>Foelix</hi> ſaid to <hi>Paul; Goe thy way for this time, and when I haue conuenient time, I will call for thee, Act.</hi> 24.26. But <hi>Foelix</hi> was remooued, <hi>Feſtus</hi> put in his roome, and <hi>Paul</hi> continues bound ſtill: So young men ſay to goodneſſe, to grace, and to God; goe your wayes for a time; and when wee are old and ſickly, then we will ſend for you, but God will turne away, Sathan will come in place, and yong men wil be left in their ſinnes. Firſt, how knoweſt thou, thou ſhalt liue till thou be old; doe not many die in their youth? And why not thou? If thou doſt, what will become of thy ſoule. Secondly, if thou liue till thou be old, how knoweſt thou whether then thou ſhalt remember God or no? Is it in thy power? Noe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe men forget God being yong, he forgets them, and makes them forget him being olde. Thirdly, if thou doeſt remember him, what great matter doeſt thou; offer it to thy Prince, will he accept it? That which is vnfit for the World, is it good enough for God? Wilt thou offer him thy old age, thy dote-age, a bagge of drie bones? Will not hee haue the firſt fruites of thy Corne, and the fat of thy flocke, and wilt thou giue the cleane corne of youth to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, and the huskes and chaffe of old age to God? wilt thou ſacrifice the fat of thy Flock to the Deuils,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17106:16"/> and the leane to God? wilt thou forgiue thy enemies, when thou canſt hurt them no longer? wilt thou giue thy goods to the poore, when thou canſt keepe it no longer? wilt thou leaue ſinne, when ſinne leaues thee? and wilt thou ſerue God when it pleaſeth thee; is God at thy command, is he bound to thee, not thou to him.</p>
            <p>It is a reproofe of thoſe that are the Proctors, and <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Patrons of ſinnes of youth. They ſay, what ſhall youth doe, ſhall they be mortified ſo young? ſhall not youth be merrie and iouiall, ſhall they bee ſober a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d graue ſo young? then you will haue no life in them belike. Others ſay, a young Saint, an old De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. A young Deuill may become an old Saint, but a young Saint can neuer become an old Deuill. O<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thers ſay, youth is youth, and youth muſt haue a ſwinge. Others of a ragged colt comes a good horſe; a knauiſh boy becomes a good man. Either <hi>Solomon</hi> was not wiſe, or they are ſtarke fooles in ſo ſaying, he ſaith, <hi>Remember God in thy youth.</hi> Let young men learne by <hi>Elies</hi> children, how they were cut off ere age came. To put off ſuch things to old age, is as if a carrier hauing many horſes, ſhould put all his carriage on the weakeſt and pooreſt, hauing many better. Young men haue many better dayes and yeeres to repent in; Delaying of repentance is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, deadly, and damnable. If a wound bee not cured before it rot, it becomes oftentimes incurable. If the fire be not quenched in time, it becomes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable; and if fleſh be not ſalted before it ſtinck, it becomes ſo vnſauorie, that it cannot bee mended.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17106:17"/> If a mote fall into the eye, or a thorne ſticke into the foot, we take them out without delay; but in things pertaining to the health of the ſoule, delay is much more dangerous. Satan ſeekes but a delay: God craues preſent repentance. It was offered by <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Pharaoh, when ſhall I pray for thee; and he anſwered to morrow, Exod.</hi> 9.10. It is offered by the Lord to man, when wilt thou that I haue mercie on thee, many anſwere, when wee are old. Miſerable was <hi>Pharaoh</hi> who delayed <hi>Moſes</hi> but one day: but more miſerable are many men, who delay the Lord for many yeeres. Some will firſt burie their Fathers, as the Diſciple would, <hi>Math.</hi> 8.21. Some will firſt go and kiſſe their Fathers, that is delight yet a ſpace in the pleaſures of this life. God will haue men now to turne, God will haue the preſent time, <hi>Bee wiſe now, Pſal.</hi> 2.10. <hi>Now therefore feare the Lord, and ſerue him, Ioſh.</hi> 24.14. <hi>Therefore alſo now ſaith the Lord, Ioel,</hi> 1.12. <hi>Conſider this now, yee that forget God, Pſal.</hi> 50.22. When <hi>Abraham</hi> was bid to circumciſe his Familie, he did not deferre it, but circumciſed them the ſame day, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.23. As ſoone as <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> was willed to ſend for <hi>Peter,</hi> hee ſent immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.33. <hi>That thou wilt doe, doe quickly in thy youth, for thou knoweſt not what a day may bring forth, Pro.</hi> 27.1. Hee that is not now willing, may hereafter bee more vnwilling. I know no difference betweene the wiſe two Virgins, and the fooliſh, but that the one did it in time, which the other would faine haue done out of time, and could not. The moſt prophane men of the world are forced, in death
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17106:17"/> to make their refuge to the Lord. Then the eye, and the hand are lifted vp vnto him, Then they crie for mercie, and deſire all others to pray for them. If men were wiſe they would doe that in time, which many would do, and do, at length when God ſent laborers into his vineyard, he that was bad goe in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, did not deferre till noone, hee that was called at noone did not deferre his comming till night. Art thou called to day, deferre not till too morrow, <hi>to day if thou wilt heare his voice, harden not thy heart, Heb.</hi> 3.15. To day is Gods voice, to morrow is the deuils, giue God to day, that is thy youth. It is one of Satans pollicies, to perſwade men to repent when they are old, till all the time bee paſt wherein Men ſhould repent. This brings many to damnation, that where in their young yeares they will not repent, in their olde age they cannot, the affections through long cuſtome of ſinnes, waxing ſtrong, euen then when the bodie is weake. Marke Satans deceit, and put not off thy remembring of God to thy old age, for thy yeeres may bee ſhortned, thy faith weakened Satan aduantaged, thy heart hardned, and it may be God in iuſtice, and the deuill in malice, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thee to remember thy Creator. How fearefull a thing is it, to fall into the hands of God, who is a conſuming fire, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29. As fire conſumeth ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: ſo the moſt ſeuere God, will conſume and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the wicked contemners of his Word. Thinke of it whiles there is hope, you young men that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your Creator, heauen and hell, leaſt you miſſe the one, and come into the other, where there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17106:18"/> no hope of eaſe; or end, which is that that makes hell, hell indeed. If all the paines of hell might haue an end, were it after million and millions of yeeres, as many as there bee Sands on the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoare, it might nouriſh ſome miſerable comfort of a releaſe in the long ruine. But this night hath no day, this Ague no intermiſſion, this death no death, to end it withall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>Before the euill dayes come.]</hi> The dayes voide of all delight will come, all ioy will faile, and ſorrow vpon ſorrow befall. There are good dayes, that is, a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happie life, wherein many good things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall vs. <hi>If any Man loue to ſee good dayes, let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine his tongue from euill,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. <hi>What Man is he that deſireth life, and loueth long dayes for to ſee good, Pſal.</hi> 34.12. And there are euill dayes, not that dayes are euill in themſelues, but accidentally.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That old age is called euill, becauſe of the many euils it brings with it. Dayes are called euill, nor ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiuely, making men euill, nor eſſentially, as if a day in its owne nature were euill; but accidentally in regard of the euill actions and euents, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to men in that day. Euill dayes are times full of Sinnes and troubles, or troubleſome &amp; ſinfull times. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Redeeme the time, for the dayes are euill, Ephe.</hi> 5.16. <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> few and euill haue the dayes of my life beene, <hi>Gene.</hi> 47 9. Euill, becauſe they were full of troubles, full of afflictions, full of dangers. Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Sufficient for the day, is the euill thereof, Mat.</hi> 6.34. That is the day brings with it, affliction, griefe, and hurts. Many
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17106:18"/> diſcommodities enuiron old men. Old age is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall weakneſſe, and a daily diſeaſe. <hi>Moſes</hi> the man of God, ſaith, <hi>The dayes of our yeeres are ſeuentie yeeres: and if by reaſon of ſtrength they bee eightie yeeres, yet is the ſtrength then labour and ſorrow: for it is ſoone cut off, and we flie away, Pſal.</hi> 90.10. If the longeſt period of dayes that men ordinarily liue, be ſo ſhort a time, and the longeſt time flieth ſo faſt, then well might the Prophet ſay, that <hi>our daies paſſe away as a tale that is told, Pſal.</hi> 90.9. The more la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours men vndergoe in their youth, the more mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſorrow in old age. The ſtronger a man hath beene, and the more labours he hath endured, the fuller of aches and paines will old age be. Old age is but a death, and Death comes flying. In old age there is weakneſſe of body and of mind; for a man is twiſe a child, and then commonly they are as children againe mewed vp, and their children are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Parents or Lords ouer them, vſing them as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents. Old men are deafe of hearing, and cannot heare good admonitions; dim-ſighted, and cannot ſee to reade, nor to goe to the Houſe of Praier; they haue feeble Knees, ſo that they cannot goe; weake Loines, and faint Armes, the Heart is afflicted, the Head ſmitten, the Spirits waxing faint, the Breath ſmelling ill, the Face wrinckled, the Stature croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, the Eyes darke, the Ioynts weake, the Noſe running, the Haires falling, the Teeth rotting, and the Eares waxing deafe, inſomuch that old age may be called, <hi>Euill dayes.</hi> In old age the Memorie failes, old men waxe dull, deafe, ſenſeleſſe, and ſpeechleſſe.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:17106:19"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> It brings many troubles, ſorrowes, and grieues with it, then men cannot helpe themſelues, nor guide themſelues, nor feed themſelues, they cannot reade to comfort themſelues, nor repent (many of them) to ſolace themſelues, they lie on their beds, as on the Racke from morning to night, crying out, ſome of one griefe, ſome of another, then they feare to die, and ſome wiſh for Death, for whom they are not prouided. Many aged people are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly vexed, and perplexed in conſcience, ſo that they ſeeke Death as a preſent eaſe, not conſidering how they leape out of the Smoake into the Flame, out of the Flame into the Fire, out of a cureable Diſturbance, into an irrecouerable Woe. How blockiſh is the manner of dying of many a <hi>Nabal,</hi> who ſtrucken with the feare of Death and Hell, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as inſenſate as ſtocks and ſtones. Aged men feare Death, but not Hell, following Death; they feare the Thunder cracke, not the Bolt; the report of the Peece, and not the Bullet; the Serjeants ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and not the Gaolers impriſonment: ſo, labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to eſcape Death, which they cannot; not Hell, which they might.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> If men learne to remember God in youth, they will bee willing to die, old age will bee a Crowne and comfort to them, for <hi>after death they ſhall rest from their labours, Reuel.</hi> 14.13. <hi>They that laboured valiantly are at reſt, Iob</hi> 3.17. They learne in youth to know God, they know that if they be once old, they ſhall ſhortly die, and then they can ſinne no more. Death, to the godly, is an entrance into ioy.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17106:19"/> 
               <hi>Michaela Caignoela,</hi> a noble Matron, ſeeing her Iudges looke out of the windowes, ſaid to her fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Martyrs; Theſe ſtay to ſuffer the torment of their conſciences, and are reſerued to iudgement, but we are going to glorie and happineſſe. And two certaine poore women weeping and crying! Oh Madame, we ſhall neuer now haue more Almes; yes, hold you (ſaith ſhee) yet once more, and plucked off her Slippers, and ſuch other of her apparell, as ſhee could with modeſtie ſpare from the fire. Death is to men as he comes attended; to the rich Man he came, followed with Deuills, to carry his ſoule to hell, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.22. to <hi>Lazarus,</hi> with troupes of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to conuey him to <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. Death is the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> feare, and the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> deſire. Death is the irreligious rich mans Enemie, but the religious poore mans Friend.</p>
            <p>It ſhewes the ſtrange folly of many men, who <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> ſpend moſt of their time in prophaneneſſe, in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, in vanities and vices. Inſomuch, that if the Lord ſhew not more then ordinarie mercy, they will be no more fit in their old age to honour their Creator, then ſo many dead men. What madneſſe is it then, eſpecially in thoſe that haue paſſed the greateſt time they can expect, to haue no care of the houre of death, and of the account they ſhall then make, when their whole time is but ſhort, as a Tale that is told. Men ſhould ſo profit by the meanes of ſaluation affoorded them, that in age they ſhould giue good example to ſuch as are young. The elder men grow, the better they ſhould be. Commonly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17106:20"/> Horſes trauell beſt homeward, or when they are almoſt come home. Hounds follow the game faſteſt when they are neereſt vnto it, finding the ſent hot, they know the game is almoſt at an end. They that runne in a Race ſtriue moſt, not at the beginning, but at the end. In naturall motions, euery thing mooueth faſteſt when it is neereſt his owne place. The Swan ſingeth ſweeteſt a little before her death: ſo ſhould it bee with old men, they ſhould then bee moſt holy, bearning the beſt fruits, doing the beſt works, they ſhould with old <hi>Simeon</hi> take Chriſt in their armes, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.28. and with <hi>Anna</hi> ſerue God with faſtings and praiers, night and day, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.87. It were to bee wiſhed that old men could ſay, as ſometime <hi>Polycarpus</hi> did, the Proconſull vrging him to denie Chriſt; I haue ſerued him eightie ſixe yeeres, and hee hath not once hurt mee, and ſhall I now denie him? And with <hi>Hilarion,</hi> Soule, get thee out, thou haſt ſeuentie yeeres ſerued Chriſt, and art thou now loth to die, or afraid of death. This is a generall and ſolemne Decree, publiſhed throughout the World, and pronounced by Nature her ſelfe, that whatſoeuer hath a beginning (ſo that it conſiſt of Matter) muſt alſo haue an end: there is nothing vnder the Cope of Heauen (except the Soule of man) which is not ſubiect to change, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Man cannot alwaies continue in one ſtate, but man groweth old. It is dangerous to waxe old in ſinne, for <hi>the ſinner that is an hundred yeeres old ſhall be accurſed, Eſa.</hi> 65.20. <hi>It ſhall not be well to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, Eccl.</hi> 8.13. Old age hath ſufficient deformities
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17106:20"/> of it ſelfe, therefore they ſhould not adde ſuch as proceed from Vice. As the labours of old men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, ſo the exerciſes of the ſoule ſhould increaſe.</p>
            <p>Seeing no man knoweth what ſhall bee, let men <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> vſe wel the preſent time, whether it be youth or age. If thou bee religious in thy youth, old age will bee welcome to thee, and the daies will not be euill, the troubles &amp; weakneſſes will ſeeme as nothing which accompanie old age, <hi>Thou wilt be willing to die, for Death will not carry thee to priſon, but to the Saincts feaſt, Reuel.</hi> 19.9. To the participation and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with Chriſt, in his heauenly ioyes and bliſſe, when the Church (his Spouſe) ſhall be fully bleſſed. Death wil come to carry old religious men to Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, a place full of pleaſures. As a man riding, takes vp one behind him, and carries him to this or that banquet: ſo Death, takes vp the religious old man behind him vpon the pale Horſe, and carries him to heauen, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Worke therefore while it is day, the night commeth when no man can worke, Ioh.</hi> 9 4. <hi>All that thy hand ſhall find to doe, doe it with all thy power, for there is neither work, nor inuention, nor knowledge, nor wiſedome, in the graue whither thou goeſt, Eccl.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Whiles we haue time we muſt doe good to all, ſpecially to thoſe which are of the houſe-hold of Faith, Gal.</hi> 6.10. Wee may not aſſigne the Lord, in what place, ſtate, condition, or in what companie we would liue, but as Strangers, waite on him, euen as the hand-maid on her Miſtris, for whatſoeuer he will allow vs: we are readie moſt commonly to bee called away by death, before we be fit, or haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17106:21"/> how to liue. Looke what care, conſcience, zeale, loue, and reuerent eſtimation of good things thou haddeſt, when firſt thou embracedſt the Goſpel, the ſame at laſt retaine, and be ſure thou keepeſt ſtill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. The more knowledge that thou haſt, take heed thou be not more ſecure. Wee ſhall not enioy the grace, which we had at the firſt, except we be as carefull now to keep it, as we were then to come by it. All our life ought to bee a prouiding for a good death, and a keeping away of woe, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by ſinne. We cannot promiſe to our ſelues one day, for Time is Gods, <hi>and Times and Seaſons he hath put in his owne power, Act.</hi> 1.7. therefore, euery day wee ought to prepare our hearts to ſeeke the Lord, and keepe them fit and willing thereto. <hi>Take heed, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, leſt at any time there be any of you an euill heart, and vnfaithfull, to depart away from the liuing God, Heb.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Oh! that there were in them an heart to feare me, and to keepe all my Commandements alway, Deut.</hi> 5.29. Our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy heart, Matth.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Euery day our thanks muſt be continued for benefits receiued, they are renewed euery morning, Lam.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Euery day we ought to watch and pray for ſtedfastneſſe and conſtancie. Euery day we must hold and keepe our peace with God, and lie downe therein, Pſal.</hi> 4.8.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note>
               <hi>And the yeeres approach, of which thou wilt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them.] Solomon</hi> meaneth, before thou waxe old. Old age of it ſelfe is a diſeaſe, if no other diſeaſe beſide happen. What pleaſure can old men take, when ſtrength faileth them, when they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17106:21"/> are not able to helpe themſelues. Their life, in this life, is nothing elſe but a returning backe againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, for whiles they are here, they walke to the houſe of their graue. Their dayes paſſe away in ſuch a manner, as if a man, being a child, ſhould ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be made a man; and after that, ſhould preſently goe backe againe, and bee a child. The more men grow in ſtrength and yeeres, the neerer they draw to the place from whence they came. <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſtrength of old men is labour and ſorrow, Pſal.</hi> 90.10. Their dayes are dayes of ſorrow, and their ſtrength brings nothing vnto them, but matter of labour and paine.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>
               </label> That the many diſcommodities and miſeries of old age, plainly teſtifie, that there is no pleaſure in it. <hi>Such as are full of dayes,</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> was, <hi>Iob</hi> 42.17. are full of miſeries. <hi>Man that is borne of woman is full of miſerie, or full of vexation, Iob</hi> 14.1. The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the laſt age is admirable, and hath need of a good Anatomiſt, to helpe the true vnderſtanding of the ſame. <hi>Then the Sunne is darke, and the Light, and the Moone, and the Starres: And the Clowdes returne after the Raine, Eccl.</hi> 12.2. <hi>The Keepers of the houſe tremble; the Strong men bow themſelues; the Grinders ceaſe, becauſe they are few; and they waxe darke, that looke out by the windowes, Eccl.</hi> 12.3. <hi>And the doores ſhall bee ſhut by the ſtreet, with the baſe ſound of the grinding; and a Man ſhall ſtand vp at the voyce of the Bird; and all the Daughters of Muſick ſhall be brought low, Eccl.</hi> 12.4. <hi>And men will dread euery high place, and feare will be in the way; and the Almond tree will
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17106:22"/> flouriſh, and the Graſſe-hopper will bee a burthen to it ſelfe, and all lust will be diſſolued, and a man goeth to his long home, and Mourners goe about in the ſtreet, Eccl.</hi> 12.5. <hi>The ſiluer Cord is looſed, and the golden Ewer broken, and the Pitcher burſt at the Well, and the Wheele broken at the Cisterne, Eccl.</hi> 12.6. <hi>And dust re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit returne to God that gaue it, Eccl.</hi> 12.7. By <hi>the Sunne and Starres darkned,</hi> is meant, the dayes loſing their light, ſo that all things ſeeme darke vnto them, euen the Sun it ſelfe. <hi>And the Clowdes returne after the Raine;</hi> that is, after they haue wept a long time, there paſſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes, as it were, clowdes, being nothing elſe but groſſe vapours, which grow thicke and fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie. <hi>The keepers of the Houſe tremble,</hi> that is, the ribs and breaſt, which keepe the inward parts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth them about. <hi>The ſtrong men ſhall bow;</hi> that is, the knees and legges ſhall loſe their ſtrength, which are the Pillars vpon the which the whole building is ſet. <hi>The grinders ſhall ceaſe, they are few,</hi> that is; the Teeth, the mouth being as a Mill, old mens teeth are few in number, and thoſe that are weake, and ſo the grinding ceaſeth. <hi>And they waxe darke, that looke out by the Windowes;</hi> that is, the eye in the head, like Windowes in a Houſe, like two lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, which giue light in order. <hi>And the doores ſhut without, by the baſe ſound of the grinding;</hi> that is, the Lips ſhall be ſhut, becauſe the Teeth and Iawes make a baſe ſmall ſound in grinding the meat, grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it badly and weakely. <hi>And he ſhall riſe vp at the voyce of the bird;</hi> that is, he ſhall not be able to ſleep,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17106:22"/> or ſleepe very little, and be awaked with euery little ſound, euen the ſinging of a Bird; this followeth, their cruditie and rawneſſe, being not able to digeſt their meates. <hi>All the daughters of Muſicke ſhall bee brought low;</hi> that is, their voyces will faile them. <hi>And men will dread euery high place, and feares will be in the way;</hi> that is, they are afraid to goe vp into high places, they are afraid to walke, becauſe a plaine way ſeemes rough vnto them; a hillocke, a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; a hollowneſſe, a great valley. <hi>And the Almond tree will flouriſh;</hi> that is, the head grow white. He nameth the Almond tree, for that doth firſt flowre of any tree, as if he ſhould ſay, old mens gray haires come on with haſte, ſometimes before they looke for them. As the flowers of trees are a ſigne of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Summer; ſo the whiteneſſe of the head is a ſigne of inſtant death. <hi>And the Graſſe-hopper ſhall be a burthen;</hi> that is, the leaſt creature ſhall bee a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, light things ſhall ſeeme heauie vnto them. <hi>And all luſt will be diſſolued;</hi> that is, all the deſire to eate or drinke, or otherwiſe, ſhall decay; becauſe all the faculties, both vitall and naturall ſhall bee weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>For man goeth to his long home;</hi> that is, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to his old houſe, from whence firſt hee came forth. <hi>The Graue is the houſe where the dead must dwell, it is the way</hi> (as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> ſaith) <hi>of all the world, Ioſh.</hi> 23.14. that is, I ſhall die ſhortly after the cuſtom of all other men. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, <hi>I goe the way of all the earth.</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 2.2. The Graue is the common houſe and receptacle of all humane bodies. <hi>Euery one ſhall ſleepe in his owne houſe, Eſay</hi> 14.18. that is, in the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17106:23"/> Graue. <hi>I know</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob) thou wilt bring me to death, and to the houſe appointed for all the liuing, Iob</hi> 30.23. <hi>and the mourners goe about in the ſtreetes;</hi> that is, weeping for the dead, for weeping is not to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued if it be moderate; our Sauiour wept for <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> his friend, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 11.35. <hi>Abraham</hi> lamented <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah, Gen.</hi> 23.2. The <hi>Hebrewes, Moſes, Deut.</hi> 34.8. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, Iacob, Gen.</hi> 50.1. The <hi>Iſraelites, Ioſeph;</hi> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>Stephen.</hi> It is not without much reaſon, that <hi>Solomon</hi> doth giue counſell, to goe to the houſe of mourning, for there is perform'd that bleſſing which Chriſt promiſeth. Heatheniſh mourning is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, which is without hope, 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.13. but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſorrow is commendable. <hi>The ſiluer Cord is loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;</hi> that is, the Marrow of the backe, which becauſe it is white, is called by the name of <hi>Siluer,</hi> this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth at the Braine, and goeth all along the bone, this in old age (ſtrength decaying) is lengthned and drawne out. <hi>The golden Ewer is broken;</hi> that is, the Braine, whoſe skin, which compaſſeth it, is yellow as gold, which being broken or hurt, man muſt needs die. Nor <hi>the Pitcher burſt at the Well;</hi> that is, the great Veine, called the hollow Veine, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not draw bloud any more out of the Liuer, which is the common Store-houſe and Fountaine, which watereth all the body in ſuch ſort, that it yeeldeth no more ſeruice then a broken Pitcher. <hi>By the wheele broken at the Ciſterne;</hi> that is, the Head, for that is like a wheele. <hi>And by the Ciſtern,</hi> is meant, the Heart, which is the chiefe dwelling of Life. When all this commeth to paſſe, then the body, which is made of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17106:23"/> 
               <hi>the duſt of the earth ſhal turn</hi> into it againe, through the ſin of our firſt parents. In death all things are recalled to their firſt beginnings. <hi>And the ſpirit to God that gaue it,</hi> hence is it, that God is called <hi>the Father of ſpirits, Heb.</hi> 12.9. that is, the maker and giuer of ſoules. <hi>He for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſpirit of man within him, Zech.</hi> 12.1. the ſoule is the hoaſt in the ſin of the bodie, not produced from the ſeed of the pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, nor from the ſoule of the parents but giuen of God, that it might viuificate the bodie.</p>
            <p>There can be no pleaſure where ſo many troubles &amp; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> ſorrows are. It is better to die then to liue. What plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is there in old age, when old perſons ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not put on or put off their clothes, cannot feed themſelues, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not relliſh their meat, nor know what day of the weeke it is, nor diſcerne good from euill. When <hi>Dauid</hi> would haue <hi>Barzillai</hi> come to him into <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that he might feed him <hi>Barzillai</hi> ſaid vnto the King, <hi>how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daies are the yeers of my life, that I ſhould goe vp with the King to Ieruſalem. I am this day foureſcore yeers old, and can I diſcerne between good or euill? hath thy ſeruant any taste in that I eate, or in that I drinke? can I heare any more the voyce of ſinging men &amp; women? wherefore then ſhould thy ſeruant be any more a burden vnto my lord the King? Thy ſeruant wil go a little way ouer Iordan with the King, &amp; why will the King recompence it me with ſuch a reward? I pray thee, let thy ſeruant turne backe againe, that I may die in mine own citie, &amp; be buried in the graue of my father, and of my mother.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19 34, 35, 36, 37. <hi>Barzillai</hi> vſed foure reaſons for his refuſall to go with <hi>Dauid;</hi> Firſt, his age, be being fourſcore was not fit for trauell. Secondly, the defect of his ſences and therefore not fit for a Princes court, he could not iudge between
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17106:24"/> ſauourie and vnſauourie, between ſweet and ſowre; he could not diſcerne by taſting good or euill in meate or drinke, or in any other ſuch pleaſant things, neither did he here with pleaſure. Thirdly, he was loth to be a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to <hi>Dauid.</hi> In Princes courts ſuch as wil not behaue themſelues as others doe, are burdenſome, if they will not be merry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions if not drinkers, they are a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. Kings will haue ſuch men with them which can diſcourſe, but I am vnable to doe it, and therefore vnfit to be a Courtier. Fourthly, it was pleaſant to him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, to thinke rather of his graue, then of a Princes Court; and therefore let thy ſeruant turne back againe: old men ſhould think not how they may liue, but how they may die godly, they ſhould prepare in life for death, and then death to them will be a paſſage to life.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Many aged perſons are weary of the world, becauſe the world is ſo full of troubles, &amp; they ſo full of paines and griefs. Eſpecially, if they feare God, for then euery houre is a day, euery day a week, euery weeke a yeere, they liue. <hi>They deſire to be diſſolued, &amp; to be with Chriſt, which is beſt of all, Phil.</hi> 1.23. <hi>They loue to remoue out of the body, and to dwell with the Lord,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.8. They be from home as long as they are on earth, here ſtrangers, vſing this World, as if they vſed it not, ſetting their minds vpon that Countrey which is aboue. Their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions be in heauen, though they be on earth, their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is in heauen, and therefore their hearts are where their treaſure is, and death to them is a paſſage to life. They feare not death, hauing a good meaſure of faith to warm them at the heart, they change not their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, nor haue their colour any whit abated, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is recorded of Miſtris <hi>Ioyce Lewis</hi> at the ſtake, &amp; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17106:24"/> other Chriſtians, euen of the fearfulleſt by nature &amp; ſexe, looked as freſh &amp; cheerly at the houre of death as at their mariage. But if men which are aged, do not feare God, they wiſh to die to be freed from paines, but they paſſe from litle paine to great, from eaſeleſſe to endleſſe, from corporall to eternall. Hell is Deaths Page &amp; Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower, attending him where euer hee goes among the wicked ſort. It is miſerable to ſee how boldly, &amp; blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch men venture on death. <hi>Theramines</hi> wrote books in praiſe of Death, as the end of all calamities. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> dies ieſting, calling for a <hi>Plaudite. Tiberius</hi> in diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. <hi>Diogenes</hi> hearing <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> cry out in his pains, who ſhall eaſe mee; offers him a knife to diſpatch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe withall. <hi>Caninus</hi> called to execution, bids this fellow remember hee had the beſt of the game. The Earle of <hi>Kildare,</hi> ſeeing his Writ of death brought in when hee was at ſhouel-boord, throwes his caſt with this in his mouth, whatſoeuer that is, this is for a huddle. If ſuch men idid know the follower of Death, they would neuer ieſt ſo, and vſe ſuch idle mirth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> Hath old age many miſeries which accompanie it, ſo that there is no pleaſure in it, but euerie day is a day of wrath, an euill day, ſubiect to ſome iudgment or other, this ſhould make the children of God lift vp their hands and hearts, deſiring to enioy that life, wherein neuer a day ſhal paſſe away in wrath, but all in loue, fauour and glorie, and wherein the dayes of our life ſhall not be a returning to death, but a going on from life to life, and ioy to ioy, when we ſhall liue to liue, and the longer we ſhall liue, the longer we ſhall haue to liue, and that in happineſſe and glorie, which daies and times ſhal neuer waſte. If we had hearts to conſider of things as they are,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17106:25"/> there is neuer a day goes ouer our head, but yeeldeth matter of ſighing and groaning vnder ſome act of Gods wrath, doe we the beſt we can. If we had the greateſt cauſes of comfort, both for this world, &amp; the world to come, that the world can affoord, or that euer any man had, yet when he ſhall ſumme his accounts, he ſhall find the daies he liues here, are but daies of euill, and he ſhall ſee more cauſe of ſorrow &amp; mourning then of ioy. Let the bitter of Gods wrath here, make vs the more ſeeke after the daies of eternitie, where there ſhall not be the leaſt croſſe, nor affliction. Mans life in this life is nothing elſe, but a returning back againe vnto death. Euery man whiles he is here, walkes to the houſe of his graue, and though he be a little longer in going backe vnto the earth, then he was comming from it, yet he doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing while he is here, but goe back to it. A tale is quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly told, a word is ſoone ſpoken, a thought is ſoone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued: ſo the yeers and daies of man are quickly ſpent.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> It may teach vs euerie day to meditate and thinke ſeriouſly of our death, and the graue. It is the place we are continually trauiling vnto. Which way ſo euer our faces are, we mooue thitherward. Euery day we are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the place of execution. A Malefactor that is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuffer death, thinks no other thing but death, were going to the place of execution, wee ſhould ſtill mind death, and euerie day prepare to die. As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of <hi>Aphimaaz, let him come and welcome, &amp;c.</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.27. ſo the faithful Chriſtian wil ſay of death, he is the meſſenger of Chriſt, he is welcome, he bringeth to me the ioyful newes of eternal life. <hi>They are bleſſed which die in the Lord, Reu.</hi> 14.13. And one day of a bleſſed death wil make an amends for all the ſorrowes of a bitter life.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
